<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and ample relation of all such occurrences as have happened in the Palatinate since the first of Iune. 1622 Stilo antiquo. Truely related in a letter, received from Doctor VVelles the tenth of Iune. 1622. And now printed the 14 of Iune. 1622.</title>
            <author>Welles, Doctor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838535</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1122:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and ample relation of all such occurrences as have happened in the Palatinate since the first of Iune. 1622 Stilo antiquo. Truely related in a letter, received from Doctor VVelles the tenth of Iune. 1622. And now printed the 14 of Iune. 1622.</title>
                  <author>Welles, Doctor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Iohn Bartlet, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Gilt Cup in Cheap-side, in the Gold-smiths Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"This belongs in the Newsbooks section following 51A."-- STC.</note>
                  <note>British Library copy reads "14 of iune" on title page, line 12.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palatinate(Germany) --  History --  Frederick V, 1610-1623 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE AND AMPLE RELATION OF ALL SVCH OC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVRRENCES AS HAVE happened in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> ſince the firſt of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1622. <hi>Stilo Antiquo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely Related in a Letter, received <hi>from Doctor</hi> VVelles <hi>the tenth of Iune.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <p>And now Printed the 14 of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1622.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the gilt Cup in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> in the Gold-ſmiths Row. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:2917:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2917:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE COPPIE OF A LETTER Sent from Doctor <hi>Welles, Relating all ſuch Occurrences, as</hi> haue hapned in the PALATINATE of Late.</head>
            <head type="sub">Received this 10. of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1622.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe not write this Letter with any deſire of publication, becauſe the beſt Compoſiters are ſubiect to the worſt cenſures, or willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to traduce, and countermand ſuch Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, as are rather framed out of coniecturall braynes then honeſt intelligence, but meerely to ſatisfie my Friends, eſpecially ſuch as are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2917:3"/>friends of the cauſe of the <hi>Pallatinate,</hi> and finde their hearts affected to the true vnderſtanding of the buſineſſe. For if in ſupplying the Preſſe there is a kind of commenditory zeale and honeſt wellwiſhing manifeſted; much more ſhall the truth it ſelfe receiue grace and favour, and be well come to all Religious hearts; as for ſuch as are otherwiſe addicted, it matters not to ſatisfie them, for <hi>Charmes</hi> will not moue <hi>Adders</hi> out of their holes. And <hi>Pharoahs</hi> heart was hardned, till he ſaw the judgements of God. To conclude this Preface, if you meane to divulge any thing I write, I pray you giue the world notice, that it is againſt my will; and Letters written in haſt are not fit for curious over-looking, or judicious exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. As for extractions, and culling out (as I may ſay) the principall poynts, it will be the better, if there be way giuen, whereby the Worke may be iuſtifiable, and the world made acquainted with information of the Truth; and ſo to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Since the Kings comming into the <hi>Pallatinate,</hi> and ioyning with Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> there hath beene many skirmiſhes, I will not call them all Battailes, in all which it hath pleaſed God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2917:3"/>to giue him happie ſucceſſe, yea, in that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Diſaſter of the Powder, in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Badens</hi> Campe, the iſſue tended to the glory of God, and the Kings eternall Honour, for he recovered more then he loſt, and gaue them all a worthy teſtimony of his valour and Horoick Demeanor, ſo that if you will giue me leaue by way of Tranſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to exemplifie ſome particulars, and I will by Gods grace ſpeake nothing but the Truth, and ſo dull and abate all the ſharpe and keene edges againſt Him, which deſire to cut the life of Reputation, did not Vertue in deſpight, like a Sunne diſpelling the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, quite diſſolue and vaniſh the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew of calumniation.</p>
            <p>Know then, that in theſe Conflicts, his Maieſtie hath ſtill beene in perſon, and ſo forward, that he hath many times ſhewed ſufficient teſtimonie of his owne particular valour, diſcharging his Piſtoll at the very firſt Encounter, in the face of the Enemie; and many times Adventuring with the formoſt, when there was great reaſon and cauſe that he ſhould haue beene more charie of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Beſides, He is a comely and handſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2917:4"/>Gentleman, and ſo compleat, that I know not whither I ſhould preferre the workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, in his compoſure of bodie, or well qualifying his minde, for he is and ever hath beene, for any thing I can heare or ſee, of extraordinary good Demeanor in all his affayres, as both his ſpeeches and actions doe manifeſt, neither deiected with Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, nor lifted vp with Proſperitie. Fayre and temperate, neither giuen to the common vice of the Dutch Nation, which is drunkenneſſe, nor yet the Engliſh, although he haue well learned the Engliſh Tongue, wherewith the moſt doe learne the Engliſh Oathes: He is ſo moderately conditioned, that there is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to behold Him, and a delight to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Him; the truth is, I never heard his worth ſufficiently ſpoken of before his comming to vs, ſo can I not ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the ſame, now he is amongſt vs. I haue inciſted the longer vpon this my poore Diſcovery, becauſe Malice heretofore hath imputed the loſſe of <hi>Prague</hi> to his negligence, or ignorance; and wickedneſſe, even at this preſent, doth dare to lay ſome aſperſions vpon Him: But to goe forward.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2917:4"/>
            <p> After the recouery of the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> and the taking of <hi>Laden-burge,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was a worke to take out the prouiſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and bring it to the Kings ſtore at <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem.</hi> For it was great and much more then was expected, ſo that the whole Army was the better refreſhed: after which another buy ſineſſe of great importance propoſed it ſelfe, and the Kings Army in as great ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe marched ouer the <hi>Rheine</hi> at <hi>Mantem</hi> bridge towards <hi>Haggenaw</hi> in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> before which <hi>Leopoldus</hi> the Emperors brother had lyen ſome ten dayes, as reſolued to ſurpriſe and beſiege the ſame by way of recouerie of ſome of his loſſes: but hearing of the Kings approch, and fearing the ſally of the towne, which was extraordinary manned with 5000 of <hi>Mansfields</hi> ſouldiers, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to draw a way about the 8 of May by your account, and tooke an order with his army to ſhift for themſelues, as he very fortunately made his owne eſcape: but the Kings army followed him ſo cloſe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him ſo farre, that they cut off moſt of his baggage, and ſeized on his carriages, where contrary to expectation was found
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2917:5"/>aboue 26000. l. weight of pouder, all his plate and much good furniture beſides, ere they ended the buſineſſe, both Colonell and Captaine, with a regiment of foote and ſix troupes of horſe, were moſt of them ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and reduced to his Maieſties ſeruice, for very few vvere ſlaine at this time: this was done when they were paſſing a bridge, vvhich as ſome ſay vvas broken, and others ſay was ouerthronged with numbers; but the former is likelieſt, becauſe two peeces of ordnance was drowned, and the King tooke two or three more; but how euer it was, or that men may vary in ſome pettie circumſtances, vve repute it a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate then that which they ſpeake of, that the Marquis of <hi>Durlach</hi> had, for though he loſt more ordnance, yet not halfe ſo many men: beſides, that loſſe is doubled by ſo many troupes as are gone ouer to our ſide, and God be praiſed are moſt willing to ſerue his Maieſtie. This, as we heare, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready printed amongſt you, but in a rouing manner, and farre from ſufficient intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2917:5"/>and therefore I thought it good, as in the reſt, to certifie you in the very truth, which howſoeuer many men may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſuperfluous, and that ſtill they heare but one and the ſame thing, yet ſure there is great contentment in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt confirmation of ſuch buſineſſes, or true relating the matter. So I go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Marquis of <hi>Durlach</hi> named in your copies the Marquis of <hi>Baden,</hi> is againe on foote, and hath altered the manner of his ſequeſtring himſelfe in a campe alone, ſo that now being ſeuen thouſand foote and 1200 horſe, as vve may ſay, he is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vvith the King and Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> being all together, to abate a little the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhes of rumour 20000 in a running ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, which is continually on foote, as the cauſe requireth, and buſineſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth; for of late they haue beene ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dayes together in the Countrey of <hi>Dermſtrat,</hi> hard by <hi>Frankford,</hi> the Prince whereof <hi>Lantgraue Lodowick</hi> hath alwayes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2917:6"/>bin a ſtraight enemy to our affaires, and a publick profeſſed friend to his Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: for it was he that the laſt yeare la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured the accord between the Princes of the Vnion and Marquis <hi>Spinola,</hi> it was he that gaue way and aſſiſtance to all the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh marches, it was he that hath ſo much extolled and magnified the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> it was he that hath taken great paines all this Winter to diſſwade the Marquis of <hi>Durlach</hi> and other Princes from taking vp armes in our aſſiſtance, vnder pretence of deſire of peace, and auoiding effuſion of Chriſtian blood: it was he that gaue eare to the Ieſuites and Prieſts in their blaſphemous railings and filthy calumniations againſt God, his Church, and the King of <hi>Bohemiaes</hi> buſineſſe. To conclude, it was he (Gods holy name be praiſed) that the King tooke priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in his owne country, and keeps him ſtill in his cuſtody. His country hath neither ſtrong townes nor fortifications, but is ſoon ſubiect to a violent enforcement, and ſo was as ſoone ouercome by our armies affoording a great ſupply of prouiſion, the hungry ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier was wel cheered, and our diſtreſſed gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2917:6"/>wonderfully relieued with good mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons and beeues, that all this Winter haue bin afflicted with great ſcarcitie and wants, hunger and cold: but now there is a new face of comfort and contentment appeareth on euery ſide. For my Lord <hi>Chicheſter</hi> is ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and opportunely ariued at <hi>Manheim,</hi> to our hearts reioycing and the Kings ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For although <hi>Monſieur Tilly</hi> our grand enemy be againe ſtrengthened from <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Bauaria,</hi> and <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> yet whether war or peace, the King is able to en<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ounter with him, and prepareth with reſolution to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all his enemies, let them increaſe neuer ſo faſt, as I muſt confeſſe they are many; <hi>Tilly</hi> of himſelfe is eſteemed 14000 ſtrong, and as our intelligence is, hath 6000 more from the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> in his paſſages and <hi>Gon ſaloes</hi> as he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpare from his gariſons, ſo that in the end of May he marched full 20000. towards the King, whoſe tranſcendent name with me is predominant.</p>
            <p>After my Lord of <hi>Belfaſt</hi> or <hi>Chicheſter</hi> was welcomed and entertained of all ſides, the King and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> departed to the army, and as we had certaine intelligence
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2917:7"/>vpon Munday the 27 of May he marched to a towne of the Biſhop of <hi>Ments</hi> aboue <hi>Frankford,</hi> called <hi>Ausburge,</hi> to meete with the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> there, vvho vvas now marching into <hi>Franconia;</hi> but before he could get to the Maine, a riuer ouer vvhich he muſt be tranſported, Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> vvith his great ſtrength and vvhole army vvas got before him, ſo that he muſt of neceſſitie fight or retire, for <hi>Brunſwick</hi> vvas not yet come vp to the riuer, nor had any notice of the Kings being ſo neare, more then that he vvould come to meete him.</p>
            <p>In breife, to fight vpon ſo great diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, was not thought conuenient. For the Countrey being ſpoyled, and vittailes ſcarce could afford them no releife: the enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrong and prouided of purpoſe, might hazard the Army. For you muſt conſider, beſides <hi>Tillyes</hi> owne forces, he had <hi>Genſalers</hi> horſe which came to him from Openham, from the Archduches horſe, ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily armed; that they exceeded the Dutch far and may well be compared to thoſe ſtrong
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2917:7"/>Cataphracts of the <hi>Romaines,</hi> which were armed from head to foote; therefore it was thought conuenient to make a Retreate, which was done in ſo good order, that to his euerlaſting prayſe, the King muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: for not with ſtanding, all they could doe, the enemy followed ſo hard that he ouer tooke them, and the horſe gort ſuch way through &amp; about the woods that skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh they muſt, and skirmiſh they did, ſo that the King returned from the Van, to be an actor in the ſame.</p>
            <p>This fight laſted in a maner two dayes, May 30. 31. and was at laſt ended ſo well, that while the Horſe encountred on both ſides: the foote retreated towards <hi>Manheym,</hi> wherein was loſt not aboue on 100. of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, but the Horſe had a ſorer conflict and a ſorer continuance, wherein the King as he had done in his firſt battaile with Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Tilly,</hi> demeaned himſelfe ſo couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly well, that his example drew on others to noble performances and remarkable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters: for amongſt many Gent. whoſe names did not at this time fall to my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2917:8"/>proportion of knowledge, among thoſe that were noted to fight moſt brauely were Colonell <hi>Ouertront</hi> Commander of the <hi>Palſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graues</hi> horſe, one Sir <hi>Iohn Maynard</hi> of <hi>Kent</hi> Captaine of a troupe of Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſe, were worthy and remarkable. Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> had one of his kinſmen, called Count <hi>Philip,</hi> of <hi>Mansfield</hi> taken priſoner, as ouercharged with numbers; diuers others might be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred to their perpetuall fame. Many were ſlain, wounded, and taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners on both ſides. The report goeth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe was 200 on both ſides, the loſſe being equal keepeth rumor from too lauiſh boaſting of peuailing, only the King returning to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim</hi> that might be ſaid he was glad it was no worſe, conſidering the accident or chance of warre. God had dealt mercifully with him in affoording him ſo good an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape and deliuerance from ſuch eminent perill.</p>
            <p>On our ſide was Colonell <hi>Galſtein</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Marquis of <hi>Durlacks</hi> horſe ſlaine, a vvorthy braue ſouldier, and a Rinegraue taken priſoner.</p>
            <p>On the Emperours part a Collonell
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2917:8"/>in compleate armour, was ſhot into the face, as he lifted vp his beauer to take the ayre: and ſundry other officers were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the ouer-maſtering forces of their Aduerſaries; ſome killed, ſome wounded, ſome ſuppreſſed, and they were glad at the laſt to part vpon equall termes; and (as we heare) Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> had no great cauſe too much to reioyce: for the horſe that eſcaped left much Armour, and the men were bruſed exceedingly. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our ſelues we eſteemed it a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, exceeding Report, that in a retreite of thirty or forty miles wee haue loſt no baggage at all, nor more men than the enemy, although their ioy exceeded, and Report had made the matter amongeſt the Biſhops ſo famous; yet there is but one trueth, and as neare as euer I can, you haue it: and therefore ſpare not to tell to both your friends and foes, that our buſineſſe doth thriue well, and by Gods gracious aſſiſtance, we ſhall make a happy progreſſion, though I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, the enemy is very ſtrong, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2917:9"/>for great ſupplies from out of diuers Countries.</p>
            <p>The ſame night his Maieſtie retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Maynheim,</hi> and ſupped cheareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Generall <hi>Vere;</hi> aſſuring that the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is twenty thouſand ſtrong, and encreaſeth his Army daily in his marches. Now if any aske where were the skouts on al ſides, where was the miſtaking, either of the <hi>Rendezuous,</hi> or the day of <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> approaches? where was the ouer-ſight that Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> did lodge himſelfe without any feare (as it were) betweene the Armies? for if <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> had come forward, how could a dangerous battel haue beene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented? I anſwere for all as well as my poore vnderſtanding will ſerue me, theſe things might bee without impeachment of martiall Policies, or true Diſcipline. For, concerning the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> he was reſolued to fight, and careleſſe of any forces his enemy could haue, ſo far forth as he might ioyne with <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> who had formerly ſent him Letters of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2917:9"/>aſſurance, hee would come to the riuer of <hi>Mayne</hi> ſuch a day. Beſides, it was a probable coniecture, that <hi>Tilly</hi> could not ſo ſodainly be ſo ſtrong, conſidering his former defeature, and <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Campe; but the truth is, moſt of the Arch-duke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> forces meant directly to ioyne with <hi>Tilly:</hi> and hee tooke aduice with <hi>Gonſales de Cordua</hi> with what expedition to goe forward: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Tilly</hi> himſelfe, hee had reaſon to preuent the miſchiefes, apprehending an irrecouerable danger, if the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> and <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> did meete: beſides, he tooke notice that <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> and more Carriages and ordnance mounted which muſt be the cauſe of ſlowe marches, and bring along with him ſome impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: laſt of all, that hee muſt paſſe ouer the Riuer, and whether by boate or bridge, if hee could get thither afore him, hee was ſure to hinder his landing, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinate his iourny. Concerning <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> he could not be ſo confident to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his time to a certaine day, becauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2917:10"/>an army in long marches are many times pulled backe from ſpeed and celerity by circumſtances, accidents and caſuall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents, as hath formerly beene apparent in memorable Expeditions, where the breaking of a carriage, or the diſmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Cannon hath hindered an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my from a whole dayes march. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, let there be no impeachment of a Souldiers credite in the buſineſſe of the warre, except apparent cowardice, follie and treaſon ſteppe in; but let euery man endeauour to do his beſt, and when diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters happen, be ready rather abſolutely to ſay, It was the will and pleaſure of God; or with modeſty to conclude as the common Prouerb is, It was the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of warre.</p>
            <p>Thus farre haue my Letters extended in the buſineſſe of the Pallatinate, and if you long now to heare of the King and <hi>Brunſwickes</hi> meeting, or of <hi>Mansfields</hi> forward marching, I aſſure you I long as much to giue you notice of the ſame
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2917:10"/>and make no queſtion, but my next Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall not only aduertiſe you how my Lord of <hi>Belſaft</hi> or <hi>Chicheſter</hi> proceedes in his Commiſſion, but ſend you the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tydings of ſome worthy exployt or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eyther tending to the diſcharging the Pallatinate of her intollerable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and grieuous enemies or the thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the cauſe in a farre better manner than many hollow-hearted would haue it, but becauſe things are dubitable, and the ſecrets which belong to God vnſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable, I leaue it to his direction and preſeruation that knoweth what is beſt for his owne glory, and the propagation of true Religion. Iuſt now as I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſeale vp my Letter, comes a Letter from Collonell <hi>Golſteme</hi> his owne hand, whom we tooke to haue been ſlaine, that hee is yet liuing a priſoner, which made much ioy.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
